Preliminary Guide to the Effie J. Taylor Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Effie J. Taylor papers
1919-1968
MS 1338
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
3.5
The papers consist of research papers, curriculum reports, photographs, memorabilia, and correspondence of Effie J. Taylor.
Taylor, Effie J. (Effie Jane), 1874-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the Yale University Historical Medical Library, 1980.
Biographical / Historical
Effie Jane Taylor was born Euphemia Jane in Hamilton, Ontario on April 18, 1874. After receiving an education in literature and drama in her hometown, she graduated from the Johns Hopkins Hospital School of Nursing in 1907. In the following years, she worked and went to school in Baltimore and New York. She became an associate professor of nursing at Yale School of Nursing in 1923. In 1926, she became both full professor at Yale and received a bachelor of science degree from Columbia University. At Yale, Taylor was both chairwoman of the nursing department and dean of the nursing school between 1934 and 1944, at which time she retired and became dean and professor emerita. Taylor served as a nurse in the army during both World Wars. Throughout her life, she advocated women's rights, greater respect for nurses, and the need for a deeper understanding of patients' needs. She died on May 20, 1970, in her hometown of Hamilton, Ontario.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of research papers, curriculum reports, photographs, memorabilia, and correspondence of Effie J. Taylor.
Medicine; Taylor, Effie J. (Effie Jane), 1874-
- Inventory
  - Memorabilia
    - Scrapbooks relating to ninetieth birthday, 1964-1965 (Box 1)
    - Scrapbook relating to "4-Cent Nursing Commemorative U.S. Postage Stamp", 1961
    - Photographs, medals, pins, nursing cap
    - Academic attire (Box 2)
  - Writings and topical files
    - Nutting, M. Adelaide (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Biographical (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - International Council of Nurses (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, writings, and other material relating to awards and honors, 1919-1966 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Lawler, Elsie (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Johns Hopkins University, Circa 1922-Circa 1967 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence and other material relating to honorary degree from Keulsa College [including degree], 1944 May-June (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Nursing organizations in Connecticut, 1962-1968 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Riddell House -St. Thomas Hospital -Publication, 1937 October 14 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence and other material relating to awards and appointments, Circa 1934-Circa 1967 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - International invitations and menus from events (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - International organizations (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Photographs (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Publication, photograph, and bulletin relating to awards (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Nightingale Training School, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Material relating to time at Yale (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Material relating to book Nursing the Patient (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Publications (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Therapeutics - Secondary Syphilis (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Miscellaneous notes (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Correspondence (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Macmillan Company (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Bulletins -after war (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Miscellaneous talks (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Nutrition in Relation to Nursing the Patient (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - University of Connecticut (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Goodrich, Annie W. (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Red Cross (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - World Health (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Stewart, Isabel (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Addresses and printed articles by Effie Taylor (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Quotations -Miscellaneous (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Army School of Nursing (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Biographical (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Nutting, M. Adelaide (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - Awards and exhibits relating to Effie Taylor (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - Tributes for miscellaneous individuals, written by Taylor and others (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - "Yearbook" of Professors at Yale School of Nursing (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Notes, correspondence, telegram, and clipping (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Oversize memorabilia (Box 5)